Shailesh Charati

CONTACT

5P105,Arya Hamsa Apartments JP Nagar 8th phase Bengaluru - 560083 scharati@gmail.com +91 9741939070

WORK SUMMARY

15+ years of experience working in Software Development of which 3+ years as Software Architect. Currently, Software Architect at Siemens Industry software

- Architecting solutions in the Systems Engineering and Requirements Management portfolio
- Architecting application integrations
- Providing technical leadership and responsible for the technical road map

Previously worked as Technical Leader at PRION (now Accenture), Senior Software Engineer at Geometric Software(now HCL Technologies) designing and developing migration tools, data analysis tools, custom solutions on Teamcenter Platform.

Competencies: Software Design, Software Architecture, Software Integration, Java/JavaScript/Python/AngularJs/Node.js

WORK EXPERIENCE

Siemens Industry Software India (Pvt) Limited

August 2016 — Present

Senior Software Engineer

- Defined the road map, architecture and led the development of Polarion ALM- Teamcenter Requirements Management Alignment which has resulted in new customer wins.
- Led the development of native JavaScript/AngularJS Requirements solution from legacy GWT solution.
- Re-architected Requirements management integration components(Microsoft Word and Excel) which has reduced cost ownership of the solution, improved maintainability and reuse.

Siemens Industry Software India (Pvt) Limited

March 2008 — August 2016

Advanced Software Engineer

- Defined the solution architecture ,design and led the development of Integration between Microsoft Visio and Teamcenter product.
- Introduced Apache Thrift (serialization and RPC) to reduce cost of ownership .Apache Thrift was later evaluated by the Platform team for building Micro services.
- Designed and developed a web based diagramming demonstrator for a major customer which eventually led to a multi-year customer funded product development initiative.
- Scoped, managed and successfully delivered Proof of Concepts (POC) that resulted in technical wins.
- Re-architected several aspects of Logistical Support Analysis solution, led development and adoption.
- Improved the import performance in Logistical Support Analysis solution by 50%.
- Managed and mentored team of external development personnel and delivered a high visibility troubled project.
- Identified customer pain points and conceptualized,led development of tools to ease the same.
- Automated the process of localization of domain solutions which drastically reduced development time.

Shailesh Charati 1

September 2006 — October 2007

Technical Leader

- Designed and led the development of Aircraft Engine Logbook generation module.
- Worked on the development of an ETL tool which turned out to be highly successful for PDM data migrations.
- Designed and led the development of an internal document management system using the Teamcenter Enterprise SDK.
- Developed data extraction client for exchanging data between Teamcenter Enterprise and third party systems.

Syntel

April 2006 — August 2006

Project Leader

■ Provided technical inputs to RFPs

Geometirc Software Solutions

December 2003 — April 2006

Senior Software Engineer

- Conceptualized, Designed and Developed a framework for data analysis tools to report corrupt data and suggest remedies which was a customer pain point.
- Worked as consultant for customer data migrations and ensured successful deployments.
- Developed data migration solution for migrating data from a legacy CAD integration product.

Geometirc Software Solutions

April 2001 — November 2003

QA Engineer

- Worked on the Quality Assurance of Teamcenter Industry focused solutions viz., Aerospace and Defense, Consumer Packaged Goods and also of migration solutions.
- Developed tools for test reporting and tools to reduce setup time for Test Environments.

KFY SKILLS

Technical:

- Techniques: OOAD,Agile,SCRUM,BDD/TDD
- Languages and Frameworks: Java, JavaScript, HTML5, CSS, Python, Node.js, AngularJS, GWT, Eclipse RCP
- Tools: Git,Perforce,CVS,Visio SDK

Others:People Management,Coaching,Mentoring

EDUCATION

M.S in Software Systems

August 2005 — August 2007

BITS, Pilani

B.E. Mechanical Engineering

August 1995 — August 1999

Karntak University, Dharwad

K.L.S. Gogte Institute of Technology, Belgaum

PATENTS

Jointly hold patent :Interactive configuration-management-based diagramming tool US 8768654 B2

Shailesh Charati